Guide to the Ralph E. Rechel Papers, 1947-1980 MS2064
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Ralph E. Rechel papers
1947-1980
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Ralph E. Rechel
MS2064
4 Linear Feet
Ralph E. Rechel Papers consist mainly of documents created by him or his colleagues during his years as a transportation analyst and consultant for various public and private organizations. The collection contains assorted memoranda, reports, journals, correspondence, testimonials, news clippings and pamphlets. These range in date from 1947 to 1980.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Historical or Biographical Note
Ralph E. Rechel received his Bachelor of Arts degree with a major in Government and Economics from Principia College in 1948. He later received a Master's degree in Public Administration from the Maxwell School at Syracuse University in 1955. While still in school he worked for the Civil Aeronautics Administration and had articles published in places such as the American Foreign Service Journal. After two and a half years he began working as an analyst in the Economic Research Department of the Air Transportation Association. Here, he dealt with the inner workings of the airline industry, its involvement with the private sector and the government, and concentrating on financial planning for the future of the worlds' air transportation. His activities also included testifying before the Civil Aeronautics Board on behalf of airline carriers in regard to passenger fares, profit sharing, and public subsidies.
By July of 1959 Ralph Rechel had moved to a private consulting practice. One of his first assignments in that organization was to work on a report dealing with national transportation policy for the U.S. Senate Interstate Commerce Commission.
In the following two decades, Mr. Rechel practiced as a consulting specialist in matters of economics and management in all forms of transportation. Some of his projects included traffic forecasting, analyses of project feasibility, financial planning, and policies for the creation of large scale urban transit systems. This work, in the United States as well as eighteen other countries, was for both public and private institutions. Many of Rechel's consulting projects were in association with R. L. Banks and Associates, Inc.
Collection Scope and Content
The Ralph E. Rechel Papers consist mainly of documents created by him or his colleagues during his years as a transportation analyst and consultant for various public and private organizations. The collection contains assorted memoranda, reports, journals, correspondence, testimonials, news clippings and pamphlets. These range in date from 1947 to 1980. There is a heavy concentration of materials from the early 1960's to the late 1970's which represent Rechel's private consulting work, often in association with the Institute for Public Management.
The collection is divided into four different series of records. The largest of these is one that deals with Urban Transit Issues and includes separate categories for Financial and Economic Issues, Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues, and Urban Mass Transportation. Contained in this series are a number of documents dealing with large scale planning for commuter services in urban environments. Most do not directly relate to the District of Columbia, but may have had an impact in the later development of the Metro rail and bus system. Safety issues are also addressed in the development of such systems.
The series termed as Air Transportation reflects Ralph Rechel's early years with the Air Transportation Agency and also contains his Master's Thesis. Many issues of passenger and cargo air travel, as they developed in the formative years of the airline industry in the 1950's, are well-documented. Also included is the Railroad Transportation series which includes information on passenger and cargo travel over the nation's rail system. Additionally, there is a small amount of material on creating light rail commuting lines outside of immediate urban areas. Finally there is a series of documents relating to other forms of transportation, specifically those dealing with watercraft usage and shipping procedures.
Collection Organization
Organized into four series: Air transportation, Railroad transportation, Urban mass transit, and Other transportation.
Taiwan; Brazil; United States; Shipping; Urban transportation; Transportation; Express highways; Ralph E. Rechel; Air Transport Association of America
- Air transportation, 1947-1977; MS2064 Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series is a collection of correspondence, news clippings, reports, memoranda and pamphlets from the years that Ralph Rechel served as an economic and operations analyst for the Air Transportation Association during the 1950's.
  These documents detail various aspects of cargo and passenger services provided by the aeronautics industry. They explore the Federal Government User Charges and National Airport programs, as well as track the development of many national and international air carriers.
  Collection Organization
  The records are contained in one document box and are date from 1947 to 1977. They are arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Air Cargo Magazine clipping, October, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
  - Airline Traffic and Financial Data- Quarterly Review, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Airlines Profitless Prosperity", undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Airway User Charge Investigation, 1952 October 01 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Foreign Service Journal, 1947 November (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - CAB Economic Presentation, 1954 November 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dollar Value of Military Passenger and Cargo Transportation, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Dynamic Air Transport"- Testimony by ATA before House Judiciary Committee, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "11th Air Transport Institute"- class lecture outlines, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Federal Airways User Charge- correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Federal Airways User Charge- memorandum, 1953 December 01 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Federal Airways User Charge- news clipping, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "The Government Travel Market"- ATA release, 1954 April 02 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "The Government Travel Market"- ATA release, 1954 April 02 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Integration of Aviation Communications and the Traffic Control in the Federal Airways System"- Rechel's Master Thesis, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Large Irregular Air Carrier Industry, 1954 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Large Irregular Air Carrier Industry, 1954 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The National Airport Program- Senate document, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Public Airport Investment and Monday Holiday Plan, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Recommendations for National Transport Policy, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Uncle Sam's Best Buy..."- Airline pamphlet, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Wings Work Wonders"- pamphlet, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - World Airline Orders for Transport Aircraft, 1957-1963 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Railroad transportation, 1968-1978; MS2064 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series is a collection of reports, testimonies, and memoranda that stem from Mr. Rechel's private consulting practice. Within the series are materials relating to the management and planning of various rail related industries. Most deal with passenger and freight services and how they relate to issues such as economics and safety.
  Of interest is the information on a merger between the Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad and Norfolk and Southern railroad. Also included is material on track sharing on long-haul rail lines and light-traffic rail studies. In relation to the series on Urban Mass Transit are document on implementation of suburban commuter railroads and possible subsidies.
  The records are contained in one document box and range in date from 1968 to 1978.
  - Analysis of Potential Light Rail TransportProjects, 1974 September 09 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Increased Freight Rates"- Statement by Richard Blackwell, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Increased Freight Rates"- Statement by Robert Banks, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Light-Traffic Railway Lines- Passenger and Freight Service Studies, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Light-Traffic Railway Lines- Passenger and Freight Service Studies, Final Revision, 1966 April (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Railroad Merger of C&O and N&W Information, 1966 April (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Recognition of Transport Responsibilities in the Federal Government, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Safety Issues for Intercity Freight and Common Carrier Passenger Services, 1978 December 28 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Suburban Commuter Railroad Subsidies, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Suburban Commuter Railroad Subsidies, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Suburban Commuter Railroad Subsidies, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Subway Station Capacity, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Track-Sharing Study-Progress Report, 1968 December 31 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Track-Sharing for Urban Transportation Report, 1970 January 30 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Urban mass transit, 1955-1980; MS2064 Series 3; 3 Linear feet
  This is the largest series in the collection. It contains reports, memoranda, correspondence, and journals from the beginning of Rechel's private consulting career through the next two decades of work.
  There is material dealing with the Economic and Financial Issues of various forms of mass transit planning, management and implementation, including economic analyses for different transit issues in the United States and abroad. Also included is information on the Capital Grants programs and governmental support for all levels of transit operations.
  Additionally, there is material dealing with General Transit Issues, including surveys of selected urban areas of the United States and Brazil. Also addressed are forms of intermodal transportation for the moving of industrial goods, specifically containerized forms of shipping. Safety concerns in transit planning, and strategic management and resource development techniques are among some of the other key subjects highlighted in the sub-series.
  Finally, there is material devoted to the Issues of Highways and Motor Vehicles. This includes the pros and cons of toll highway development and usage, motor vehicle safety, fuel costs for passenger vehicle commuting, and regulations for taxi's.
  The records are contained in six document boxes and are arranged alphabetically.
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Allocating Operating Expenses by Transit Route and Service Period, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Capital Grants Program, 1970 August (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Capital Grants Program, 1970 August (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Economic Feasibility Studies, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: "Economic Measurements"- Memo to Gordan Murray, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Estimates of Prospective Capital Investment in Urban Public Transportation, 1969 October 15 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Financing Capital Investment for Public Transportation, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Financing Transit- UMTA Publication, 1979 July (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Handbook on Transit Finance- Comments and Conclusions on Major Issues, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Loan Guarantee Project Information, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Measuring State and Local Government Fiscal Effort for Urban Mass Transportation, Vol. I, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Measuring State and Local Government Fiscal Effort for Urban Mass Transportation, Vol. I, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Measuring State and Local Government Fiscal Effort for Urban Mass Transportation, Vol. II, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Metropolitan Transportation Project- "Delivering Federal-Aid Funds to Metropolitan Areas,", 1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: The Present Condition and Characteristics of the Transit Industry and How They Evolved, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Public Funding Sources, 1971 June 03 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Public Funding Sources, 1971 June 03 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Reduced Fare Services Development, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Revenue, Expenses, Investment and Operations Data for Urban Transit Operators,Tables IA-IIB, 1960-1970 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Revenue, Expenses, Investment and Operations Data for Urban Transit Operators, Tables IIIA-VIB, 1960-1970 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: The Traditional Need for Profitable or Breakeven Operations, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Transportation and Urban Economic Development, 1969 November (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Urban Passenger Transportation- Paper on Financial Powers, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Urban Transportation Fund- paper proposal, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Economic and Financial Issues: Urban Transportation Fund II Material, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - General Transit Issues: Alternative Transportation Systems, 1973 December 09 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - General Transit Issues: Alternative Transportation Systems, 1974 February 28 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - General Transit Issues: Alternative Transportation Systems, 1974 February 28 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - General Transit Issues: Automated Guideway Transit, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - General Transit Issues: Brazil Transport Report- Rio de Janeiro, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - General Transit Issues: Brazil Transport Survey- Phase II, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - General Transit Issues: Center City Transportation Program Information, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - General Transit Issues: Christian Science Monitor, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - General Transit Issues: Containerized Traffic- Geographic Distribution Analysis, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - General Transit Issues: Elderly and Handicapped Transportation Issues, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - General Transit Issues: Function of Organized Representation to the U.S Congress, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - General Transit Issues: General Transportation Memorandums, 1969-1974 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - General Transit Issues: Geographic Scope for Transportation Plans, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - General Transit Issues: Global Survey of Potential Urban Transportation Investment, 1971 June (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - General Transit Issues: Government Regulation Activity, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - General Transit Issues: Hourly Passenger Capacity Standards for Judging Potential Application ofVarious Modes in Urban Transportation Planning, 1974 November 25 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - General Transit Issues: Information Work Program for, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - General Transit Issues: Intercity Passenger Transportation, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - General Transit Issues: Intermodal Containerization Trends and Problems, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - General Transit Issues: Metropolitan Transportation Project- "Evolution of Work Programs", undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - General Transit Issues: National Issues in Intercity Transportation, 1974 July 25 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - General Transit Issues: Palm Oil Transportation, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - General Transit Issues: The Present Condition and Characteristics of the Transit Industry and How They Evolved, 1971 September 27 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - General Transit Issues: Regulation of Demand-Responsive Passenger Vehicles, 1975 June (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - General Transit Issues: State Departments of Transportation Memorandums, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - General Transit Issues: Teheran Transportation Policy, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - General Transit Issues: Transit Management Program, 1976 December 27 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - General Transit Issues: Transit Management Program, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - General Transit Issues: Transit Resource Productivity Demonstration, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - General Transit Issues: Transportation Journal by American Society ofTraffic and Transportation,Summer, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - General Transit Issues: Transportation Policies and Energy Conservation, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - General Transit Issues: Transportation Research Forum- Rechel Papers from Annual Meetings, 1963-1969 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - General Transit Issues: Transportation Safety Issues, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - General Transit Issues: Transportation Safety Programs, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - General Transit Issues: UMTA- correspondence, 1968-1974 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: Automobile Operations and Gasoline Costs, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: An Economic Evaluation of Toll Financing for Highways, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: An Economic Evaluation of Toll Financing for Highways, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: An Economic Evaluation of Toll Financing for Highways, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: Economic Results of Highway Improvements in Appalachia, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: Exhibits of Laurentian Transit Inc. before Quebec Transportation Board, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: Gasoline Sales Distribution, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: Highway Research Record- "Transportation Planning for Natural Resource and Recreation Development,", 1972 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: Mass Transportation Tax Study, 1974 January 21 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: Motor Carrier Safety Regulations, 1978 October 31 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: Motor Vehicle Transportation Memorandums, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: Paratransit Services and Transit Subsidy Problems, 1969-1979 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: Public Paratransit Regulation, 1976 February (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: Reducing Pedestrian-Motor Vehicle Friction, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: Taxi Regulations, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: Toll Highway Operations Information of the Florida State Roads Department, 1966-1967 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Highway and Motor Vehicle Issues: Work Program of Economic and Traffic Analyses, 1967 August 10 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Other transportation, 1973-1975; MS2064 Series 4; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series consists of four folders that have been grouped together because of their disassociation with other materials in this collection. Included are reports and memoranda dated from 1973 to 1975 regarding information on different forms of water transportation in the U.S. and Taiwan. Highlighted are the use of high-speed watercraft, harbour usage, open-water shipping and military transport services.
  The series is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Economic Impact of Open Registry Shipping, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - High Speed Watercraft Available for Transit Service Demonstrations, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Military Sea Transportation Service- Merchant Marine Industry Relationships, undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Taiwan- Harbour Port User Charges and Other Transit Material, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 17)